[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software this is Josh long
from software engineering radio with me
today is Andrew clay Schafer Andrew
studies focused on math and science then
he got into computers to support his
wife in medical school and soon
thereafter started working as a
developer for a venture funded startup
he worked on the team that expect the
fusion i/o cards an e-commerce software
as a service solution before co-founding
puppet labs and focusing on
infrastructure and operations along the
way he became fascinated with agile
software methodologies and was lucky
enough to have access to Alistair
Colburn and the Salt Lake agile
roundtable this had a big impact on his
worldview and definitely influenced a
lot of the ideas and practices that we
now call DevOps he later joined pivotal
to focus on cloud foundry and to
continue that journey full disclosure I
Josh long also work at pivotal so
welcome Andrew thanks for having me my
pleasure
our pleasure I haven't listened
frequently in the present day but I used
to listen to this podcast a lot back in
2008-2009 we find it's fairly cyclical
people listen sometimes they disappear
and then they come back it's always a
good time when they come back so today
we're going to talk about this idea of
the next generation platform as a
service whatever that means if that word
even holds water today what is
platform-as-a-service
what do we mean when we talk about that
well this is one of my least favorite
word's and I've written a few blog posts
and explained this in several different
ways but the main thing that we're
talking about when someone says platform
as a service or you know even worse they
say Pass is a set of API for doing
deployments that allows you to interact
with you know pushing some artifact into
some runtime that is you know
usually gonna do some work for you to
keep it up in scale at least that's the
way that it's it's usually defined if
you look at things like the the NIST
definitions unfortunately and we can
talk about this a little bit more the
word became very nebulous and so there's
a lot of things that people claim a
platform to service or labels platform
and service which aren't really the same
thing so it's hard to compare apples to
apples and then I think there's
emergence of a new thing which is when
you think about the API so allow you to
do these deployments and there's a bunch
of examples and people will hold up
things like Heroku or an app engine and
as you're you know some of the first
movers in the platform's the service
space but those them those things you
know by by virtue of being services are
also applications and does it take to
deploy and operate those what does it
take to put the full lifecycle
management into rows as a service the
platform itself and I think that's some
of the work that we're trying to do
right now it's something that is
typically taken care of by something
like infrastructure as a service or
where does that meta management come in
I think infrastructure is service well
it's in some sense bleeding or has bled
into what people originally called
platform as a service there's a little
more narrow definition so infrastructure
as a service typically refers to the
api's that will give you access to
things like virtual machines some
storage primitives and networking
primitives you know the the de facto
standard quote-unquote infrastructure as
a service is really Amazon ec2 Amazon
Web Services but then you also have some
relatively advanced offerings now from
places like Microsoft and Google and
then there's a whole host of other you
know smaller kind of niche boutique
infrastructure with service or cloud
providers so all of them are doing
different things but I think it's fairly
common to be able to expect to get VMs
back and some control over networking
and storage but did
things that we talk about it when we say
infrastructure-as-a-service are they
what we are what you're referring to
when you say that there's something that
has to manage the platform is it itself
what is that piece so in the course of
my career I've been lucky enough because
of some choice in some circumstances to
to see some very impressive web
infrastructure and participate you know
both as a developer and an operator and
in some cases almost like a business
owner but the the typical management of
those things has to be provided by
something else so if you're running an
application you have this full life
cycle of things you have to deal with
and I think one of the things that this
represents at least in my mind is the
transition from software that's
something that was shipped on CDs to
software that runs on a server that is
provided as a service this you know
thing we call the Internet that's
transforming everything we kind of take
for granted now that you're talking
about soft we're talking about services
when people say software's eating the
world you know and I've been I've been
wanting to say that as well as kind of a
narrative to support a point but the the
real thing that's happening is is this
convergence of the network with the
compute power with the connectivity so
the the software didn't also didn't get
hungry software or eating the world is
not a new thing we've got software for
decades what's new now is we're all
connected to this fabric on the network
with relatively cheap compute power and
most of us have what would have been
supercomputers a few decades ago in our
pockets so that's a very interesting
time to see that and so at the point
where those things are services that
have to run on servers they need to be
running or they don't exist software as
a service that is not running it does
not exist it's not anything it's nothing
so I think one of the things that
represents is a transition to
recognizing the the full role of
operations the full role of all these
things have to happen so it's not just
about deployment deployment is the ante
deployments just the baseline price you
pay to get to the to the
for the problems you you need to build
the rest of that stuff and you deliver
value I see what you when you first is
said that there was something beyond the
thing that was just running the
applications I was expecting that to be
some sort of discussion about for
example Bosch and now I see that you
actually had a much larger Bosch is of
course some I mean we can come back to
blush later but I mean wash wash will
fill certain roles it is you know in the
parlance of the day you know with the
rest of the kind of DevOps tooling it's
it's a bit of configuration management
mixed with some orchestration mixed with
some health checks so that gives you
some of the pieces to do the lifecycle
management but there's a there's really
you know a checklist of things you need
to do to do this in a mature way you
need to be able to you know put code
onto the servers and get it started
running you need to be able to have some
baseline monitoring and metrics if you
don't know anything about your apps that
are running and at the point where you
have a non-trivial app you might have
hundreds or even thousands of nodes that
are doing work if you can't get some
insight into that at a glance then
you're totally flying blind and at the
point where something is wrong you know
that when the customers start calling
you because the applications down we're
even going to start so over time you
know and this is sort of also
representative a transition from there
was the transition from from CDs to
services but there's also a transition
what from what I'll call ITIL you know
these really policy heavy top-down heavy
frameworks for doing service management
to the DevOps style of service
management that that we're seeing and to
media loss this really represents the
the best practices and the tooling and
processes and cultures that emerged from
high-performing teams working to go
faster and safer and it's really about
both of those in equal proportion if
you're if you're going faster but you're
not actually stable you know in
stability in this sense is different
than the old thinking which is
minimizing the number of incidents
in in the new model the DevOps model
it's really about minimizing the time to
recover and if you can get the the time
to recover from something close to zero
or zero then it doesn't matter if you
have an incident because your recovery
time is so small ah that's a very that's
a very mature perspective things will
fail well then you take it a step
farther and you introduce things like
the the chaos monkey which is actually
systematically destroying things causing
failures on 9:00 to 5:00 though when
somebody can intervene hopefully right
but if you ever if you ever have an
actual outage from those types of
failures then then that's a bug that
gets remediated and you should never
have that same failure again that's why
you run these types of destructive
processes or do the drills near the
gamedays is so that when that happens
for real like it's not for real because
it's just it's nothing it's in its your
software is is taking care of itself
there's also this also relates to a lot
of stuff we could talk about with the
frameworks we're working on but there's
there's a notion of you know
self-healing so if you build things a
certain way I'm particularly if you if
you've done sensible things to manage
state then you can you can lose a
significant fraction of your
infrastructure with no no impact to the
customer no impact of this service so
for the audience the chaos monkey refers
to a set of software released by Netflix
designed to systematically destroy
random vectors of the of the system
including hard disk access network
access being able to just kill random
processes just it does random things on
running machines for Netflix so it's a
little bit Amazon specific it's part of
the Netflix open source and now there's
the simian army so there's the you know
then the first was this chaos monkey
that does way you're describing but now
there's things that you they inject
latency they do you know whatever things
that yeah they might preserve the things
and you just want to
understand the application in a way that
you can relate to it there's a I forget
his name but it's the one of the authors
of Erlang it has a great quote and we
could go look it up and put it in the
notes but he made he made a comment that
you it's not Joe Armstrong it's the
other one he said he said that if you
don't experiment before you go and you
know put things into production and
production is always an experiment and I
think I think a lot of people live that
day to day everyday
the fear well that's a natural segue for
the next point moving to production one
hopes is friction-free and as it should
be predictable we should have some sense
of what is going to happen and DevOps is
a big part of that production deployment
should be a non-event right that's what
we're striving for and a couple of
things I think first this idea of having
a consistent workflow for you know going
from development to production from the
developer perspective and the operations
perspective from the development
perspective what does a what does
development look like locally what does
it mean to the point application that is
consistent in production with a on
something like a cloud like like a
platform as a service what does it mean
to describe that how that application
lives this is a this is a very broad
question and there's you know certainly
the way that some of this technology
were working on dustings the original
platform the service that you had with
something like Heroku then you have an
artifact which is some bits of code and
you push it into the system and the
system basically and there's all broke
is all based on essentially git repo so
you push thing into the git repo that's
your Heroku repo and then Roku has some
events that get triggered and it does
analysis of what that is and then it
decides that it is a java application or
a ruby application and then it does the
right thing to to bring that up and then
you have some knobs for being able to
scale things up and down but in that
workflow there really wasn't necessarily
you know desktop deployment
and then in production deployment well
you would typically be working with that
model you know and some of these things
have have built in so it's like Ruby and
Royals have sort of built in testing
models that you run locally with the
server Java has very similar things
depending on what you're using the IDE
support all this stuff and you know
there's this kind of equivalence for all
the different stacks so the actual
testing would typically be pushing to
another environment that was your test
environment but it would still be that
remote cloud platform that was gonna
provide the environment and then run
whatever you know so I think one of the
things that was missing a little bit
here and maybe this will be obvious to
the audience and maybe it's not is that
this whole thing is sort of founded on
great hygiene and development practices
starting with not even 12 factor but
just version control testing you know I
don't know if you want to get so
religious about test-driven development
as as we are at pinball but it's
reassuring to have some algorithmic way
to verify that things are correct before
you put them into production and if you
look at the models people are moving to
now with stuff like the the continuous
delivery models then if you don't have
continuous delivery based on a fairly
solid foundation of continuous
integration then then pushing things to
production faster is probably not doing
yourself any favors you can hit walls
really fast yeah you can bring
everything down because you and if
you've never I don't know I mean I
crashed applications more times I could
count over my career typically I also
was able to recover most of them rather
quickly but the the things that humans
assume are not always correct and if you
can codify that and protect yourself
with you know your own test Suites and
code reviews and the rest of this sort
of hygiene that the people will you know
and there's it gets a little religious
but there's sort of patterns of success
and one of them is really testing and
hygiene and having like a nice
foundational workflow and this is before
you get to something like the
architecture
implications of 12 factor or you know
some of these other things I don't know
if that's too much jargon for people we
should probably explain what that is a
quart minute I want to revisit that idea
of local development that you can trust
will look something like what's gonna
happen in the production environment
whatever that means in this case we're
talking with you know cloud you're not
gonna run the whole thing locally at
least not right now and so I actually
you mentioned Heroku earlier they they
put forth this set of principles these
guiding principles that you could use to
build applications that were divorced
from their environment and you can
easily move them from one environment to
another things like exposing services
like databases and so on as as backing
services these are the this is of course
the 12 factor manifesto is that the only
way to do it these days are are there
other ways to get a consistent feel it's
certainly not the only way to do that so
if you frame things against the the 12
factor model and that's a big part of
the the stuff that goes on with some of
the stuff we're doing with cloud foundry
and pivotal obviously but the real thing
that that does is allows you as the
operator of something like Heroku to
make certain promises so the 12 factor
math Festo is really representing a
contract between the expectations of the
application and the and the platform and
if you are going to do things that
adhere to that contract then you get
these other benefits and if you do
things if you want do things that are
outside that contract and you can't
really use the platform or you can't use
the platform's effectively or at least
to these other failure things so you
know obviously the thing that people
coming from you know some of the older
app server models they initially trip up
on things like sessions and and how you
deal with state and these other things
so the they clean separation between the
a stateless container which you can
essentially scale horizontally at will
you can afford to lose them if you don't
have session state then any anything can
serve that you know it's basically like
a functional request so that the
replacement of the container with
another one is transparent to genuine
like no Nia even has to know if bunch of
them disappear so so that contract gives
you a bunch of constraints on one hand
but it also gives you a lot of
operational advantages on the other
right and so that for example the film
between the application and its
environment becomes vanish like a small
it's just these environment variables it
becomes configuration files things
things that are easy to duplicate in my
local machine as well as on some sort of
platform as-a-service or you know some
sort of runtime what additional benefit
does having something like a container
give on top of that why would I need a
container yes sure I'm a moment ago I
mentioned that you know the first
generation of these were really about
pushing code into some fabric and then
it would build a stock and pirozhkis
actually been based on Linux containers
for a long time so under the hood they
were they were using that but then
recently it's become popular and and I'm
actually fond of this and people usually
refer to this approaches immutable
infrastructure which is that you you
package the the full machine image so
you don't you kind of get yourself out
of the dependency management problems a
lot of people have dealt with and it
really represents a failure of us to
solve the shared library problem in a
meaningful way but by packaging up the
actual all the dependencies in one
deployable artifact then you get a bunch
of advantages with consistency and then
the only difference there is and you
still don't get rid of all your problems
or having differences between the
different environments but you're able
to guarantee that the at least the bits
on the on the disk are the same and that
they'll they'll behave you know modulo
some environment variable so obviously
if you don't connect them to the right
databases or you do do silly things in
the environment that has a bunch of
conditional logic in the code then then
you kind of run yourself into problems
and I always thought it was a like I
worked on products before and I always
fought with people about logic in the in
the code where they're like the the
application knows what's environment is
in I always thought it was a terrible
terrible cause Mill and I always work
very hard to try to try to remove those
or encourage people not to do that but I
think anytime your your logic has to
know what what environments are in then
you set yourself up for these
catastrophes we
on a totally different code path in
production as you are in test and by
definition something hard to test right
because he like went out or you went out
of your way not to test it right when we
talk about containers I think maybe we
left a little little bit further ahead
what is a container Linux container what
does it refer to so this is something
that was really accessible it's been in
use for a while and an accessible game
when he was sort of a systems person and
actually is worth mentioning a little
bit of history so there's a bunch of
stuff going on with virtualization and
most people sort of understand what
virtual machines are and what a virtual
machine is and you know well I don't
wanna get too into the weeds with the
nuances of virtualization versus
whatever but you you essentially have a
way that you're emulating the hardware
and then you run an operating system on
top of that emulation so hypervisor is
providing interfaces that for all
intents and purposes or most intents and
purposes look like a machine and then
you you boot a new kernel and you're
able to run Linux or Windows or whatever
and I think most people or a lot of
people are familiar now with the cloud
offerings and those are using virtual
machines or or you maybe you're using
vagrant or some local virtualization to
do things and it's nice like you know I
can you people used to do dual boots on
their laptop I don't see a point of
doing that now because I can run in
fusion or one of the VirtualBox or some
of these other options I could run it
blue or Windows or whatever I need as a
virtual machine I don't need to go
through and set the actual booting on
that on the physical hardware and then
at some point and this is in the Linux
world this didn't get into the mainline
kernel until 2007 it came from Google so
the stuff people are calling Linux
containers right now are really about C
groups in these spaces and some other
functionality to do quotas and some of
the stuff but it's basically features of
the Linux kernel that isolate the access
to resources and visibility so the the C
groups are functions and it all looks
under the hood it all looks like this
file system because everything in UNIX
is
and you manipulate things and you set up
these hierarchies of limitations on
things like CPU and memory and then
namespaces have to do with visibility so
a collection of these hierarchies of
seat groups and namespaces set up
environment where a process that you
start on that machine under those C
groups and namespaces looks like it's
the only process running on that system
and the C groups and namespaces are
combined with these route file systems
so if you've ever used to route or
that's basically a new mount point so
you say that you want to start a new
process under the C groups and
namespaces so you're getting isolation
and limitations on visibility and and
access to resources and then you're
gonna start them on a new route file
system so that looks like it's a it's a
new machine you can't see anything above
wherever you're mounted in sarena
whatever you kind of mount it as a new
file system is your route it's the same
mechanism that UNIX uses to mount a disk
drive for example your mount your
menteng a virtual file system so to
speak well you're you were mounting it
but you're actually switching the route
so you nothing nothing beyond what you
just mounted is is visible to you in the
file system right so so if you think
about what's happening and what I what I
see is a lot of exuberance around
projects particularly docker has a lot
of adoption and to me that is a
usability bug that they were able to fix
that made this technology accessible to
the average developer who might not have
had the you know the the background or
the patience to go and like figure out
all the stuff to set up the root
filesystem and process management so
with some sensible defaults and some
tooling it's it's relatively
straightforward to get your you know
default docker container running with
kind of whatever you want and it's a
pretty nice workflow that is social so
that's the that's the thing that drove a
lot of the adoption is that you have
this named index into these images that
you can share
across the community and we we do that
law inside pivotal and you know we're
using and we'll talk about lattice maybe
a little bit later but just just being
able to have this social workflow or
like hey I just pushed this thing just
like you you have this transformation of
open source and the way people work when
you get github and that socialize that
work that now Dockers socialize the
sharing of these containers so you can
say not hey here's this thing you know
go build it but it's actually a package
you know complete file system that you
can go run whatever applications so it's
sort of becoming a new packaging system
for sharing these route file systems and
then dock it also provides some tools to
do the the runtime environment and some
inspection and they're actually starting
to work more on some more platform
features as well but that's the that's
the real big breakthrough there was this
usability bug and accessibility bug that
let everyone use the the containers and
that and you know consequently this is a
really interesting story if you think
about it in the larger context that
darker came from tooling that dark cloud
had insight into from trying to build
the platform as a service so they were
they're funded to wear the platform as a
service and they they weren't terribly
successful at getting a lot of adoption
but the insights that they had working
on that led to you know what now is kind
of become what you know one of the more
prolific projects so there's other
people working on other approaches as
well and I don't think it's I think it's
a foregone conclusion that now that
would be the only thing but the the fact
that you have you know I think over a
hundred thousand dollar images right now
that you can go pull and have a bunch of
stuff in them that you could you know
run is uh is pretty cool it's a you know
and we do that we do the docker hub
stuff with some of our projects and some
of our CI and it's obviously a big part
of lattice as well docker hub of course
is the repository you were referring to
earlier that socializes these images is
yeah so duh so what it does is it gives
you this named index into the repository
just like you'd have you know a hash or
whatever on on your git repos and so
then you can you can specify a new
docker so you say like a docker file
they would say here's my here's my image
and you could start where you left off
with the other one so you it so gives
you some workflows where you know you
could as a team work off the same base
image or someone could do one part and
then put it into the repository and some
other team could take and you know do
whatever else they want with it after
that like layers layers it was it's -
it's actually that's a it's built on the
layering forest filesystem okay it is
very that's a the best way to describe
it because that's how it works
its layers so these containers is it now
a more practical to describe and develop
your application in terms of a container
locally does that further assure us that
we have you know an identical behavior
for development and deployment well it
doesn't give you identical behavior I
mean depends on a bunch of the logic and
scaffolding around it so there's we
already talked a little bit about the
the thing that people are calling
containers right now is really features
in the Linux kernel that are taking
advantage of the of the tooling to be
able to set up these runtimes on these
root file systems and it's it's really
exciting but then like there's a bunch
of other stuff you have to do to solve
deployment and there's obviously pieces
of that in in play and some of the stuff
we're working on but if you think it's
our I used this metaphor in in a
presentation I just gave and I think
most people have seen at least pictures
of the intermodal shipping container
that people put on the boats and send
back and forth and they put on the
trains and the trucks in the in the
cranes and and all the stuff that has to
happen to make it in the there's there's
a fascinating book called the box
someone thought this was interesting
enough to write 400 pages about it and
and the impact that I had on on global
trade was
one it was not really it was not really
anticipated the impact it has now 90
percent of the non bulk transport goes
through shipping containers so there's
still some transport where it's like
it's both transport of some good some
commodity like oil or grain or something
that won't be on a shipping container
but most kids are gonna be through
shipping containers ninety percent is
the is the thing that I read and those
shipping containers they were
essentially the same since 1970 till
today but what has changes the is the
rest of that infrastructure and the
scaffolding and the logistics to be able
to take those things and put them on the
ships more effectively to take those
things and put them on the trains the
cranes the the trucks and then you know
even even every single here's an
interesting thing especially from the
perspective of talking about doing these
software deployments every shipping
container has a number and they're
tracked right so then how does how does
that whole system evolve to you know it
didn't start out that way and now we're
getting to where this is actually this
is happening right now and some of the
projects we're working on will probably
impact this but every container will be
connected to a sensor network and you
could get to the point where you know
specialized containers have all sorts of
things and guarantees and SLA is about
temperature or you know shock or
whatever and and that evolution is not
really stopping so these right now what
I think we have represents that
intermodal container so we're at
nineteen seventy and people are working
to build the rest of those you know
purpose-built ships and trucks and
trains and cranes to do the rest of the
stuff the best possible way and we made
progress and
you know some of the stuff we're able to
do right now is pretty impressive but I
feel like there's there's still a long
way to go to get to the like that I
don't see the evolution slowing down and
it's a it's pretty fun to work on it
what is then in specific terms what does
the 2015 version of
the runtime the software runtime that
isn't just about intermodal containers
what is that scaffolding you know if we
had to if you had to point at the thing
that is mapping the progress you've just
described in the actual shipping
container industry what does that look
like today is that platform-as-a-service
I think it has platform features
functionality you know if you get to the
point where you're deploying the
containers as the first first-class
primitive then then we're there but I
still think there's a lot of benefits to
some of the build pack and the code
artifact methods as well even if it ends
up creating container later just because
it gives you a little bit more control
especially from the perspective of doing
things when you have something like
ghosts or heartbleed and you need to
patch an infrastructure we run a massive
platform is a service that has collapsed
the complexity of solving something like
patching goes to getting the patch and
in an hour later all your containers and
all of your virtual machines are all
patched and that wouldn't be possible if
you didn't have a really great system
for for mapping the hygiene so I think
just getting the the containers and
putting them into a system and you know
calling that good is one thing but if
you don't have the kind of the
bookkeeping and the infrastructure and
the logistics to it to manage them like
some of the stuff that we're working on
then then you saw that that first level
deployment problem but you still have a
bunch of day two and going forward
problems that remain unsolved and and
you and you're right back to the same
the same type of procedure that you'd
have today if you're if you had a bunch
of virtual machines and they're all
deployed and you didn't have great
inventory of what images and what patch
sets are on them now I'll sit in you
have heartbleed what do you got to do
you got to go and it ends up being a
long week for for many organizations
auditing every container worst case
absolutely spelunking
what does the you mentioned a build pack
what does that specifically refer to
this goes back to Heroku and it's in
some ways so I have a cord I've been I
put it on Twitter months ago but I keep
saying it now and that is a they was
sufficiently advanced docker build
pipeline is indistinguishable from a
bill pack and basically the idea of the
bill pack is that you you push this
artifact that you want to deploy and
that could be rails or a war or jar or
whatever and then there's a couple
there's a couple steps that happen
and the first one is the detect phase
and this is this is straight Heroku so
the build packs that we use in Cloud
Foundry are derived from parochial and
most of them will work in both places
the only the only thing that doesn't
work is if there's a if there's a nuance
difference in the underlying base images
so some of the dependencies might
network but the the detect phase will
run some logic and it will say based on
you know whatever and it it's some of
its like regex or the file types or
whatever and it figures out okay like
this is this is a jar so that's a Java
Runtime and so then and these are all
configurable so you could have it do
whatever you want but it's basically
going to lay down something like Tomcat
or jetty or whatever you have a
configure to do and then and there's a
you know that stuff's evolving itself
and I know you know a lot more about
that than I do but then that Java stack
is layered on top of a root filesystem
you know running or not running but a
operating system and that could be a
blue or red hat or you know the core
lass or one of these others and then the
the build pack lays down the stack and
then that cherry on top is the
deployable artifact and then that is put
into the to the framework of the
platform and then started and that that
process happens detect and then the
compile and then there's some kind of
like close compilation steps to do some
configuration but the output of that
process what is that is that a container
or what is that well
is actually a container it's a it's a
root filesystem the insight that the
docker had was well let's just make that
a deployment artifact in and of itself
and let people ship those around
now that you know network and storage is
relatively cheap but in the in the past
and this is this is changing
Hiroki like you didn't have a way to
eject your container so you pushed your
Ruby on Rails code into Heroku and under
the hood the build packs were making a
container and you had no way to push
eject and like get that container back
out so that meant that you were forever
wondering what the final the the final
runtime result was always going to be
different for what you had locally I
don't know if that's necessarily true
especially if you're in a mindset where
you're like your local development is
not that different than your production
development and then like all these
things come down to me to managing
dependencies and and at least you know
90% of the problems people run into so
so I think most people get into a point
where like you have a pretty good
iteration your dependencies are in place
in both your environments and then you
can iterate pretty faster than everyone
so well when people really run into
problems in my patient is when those
upstreams change you know especially if
you have I don't know like Ruby you
change one version of one gem and like a
bunch of stuff broke right and it's the
same for most of these runtimes where
they're there's this chain of
dependencies and you know small
inconsistencies in or incompatibilities
in those in those dependencies can cause
this cascading failure and I think you
went into that with pretty much any
stack sure anything that resolves
dependencies over the network which is
basically they even have them for C now
so unless you're pinning your versions
down you're gonna get in trouble
pre container days whenever I ran
infrastructure I never would pull
packages from from the internet I always
thought that the best hygiene and I
still have K this pretty strongly is to
maintain local package so then your your
deployment artifacts are controlled by
you
your change management process now
includes rigorously testing and great
hygiene to pull in those up streams as
you know you need patches there's
security whatever you know this acetates
changing those things and the the gating
functionality is just to bring those
into the local repositories but you
would never deploy anything that came
right from the unfettered access to the
Internet
right so that discipline that discipline
to get that here at a for mention
hygiene I don't imagine that's easy to
come by that's something new as often is
not what the hopefully that's something
you can push to the platform to take
care of for you I mean one of my goals
with all this and this was you know
going back to the puppet days and the
DevOps days and all the rest of it the
goal has always been to enable
innovation to enable the the
organization to deliver so the the thing
that I want to get in a platform and you
know whether I'm building something from
scratch with configuration management or
now you know with these more opinionated
integrated solutions like Cloud Foundry
I want to make it the easy thing to do
the right thing right if it's if I mean
that's where people run into problems
with with hygiene is when it's it's
super hard to do the right thing you
have all these pressures to deliver the
business you know I I don't know anyone
who's ever been in a software project
where there wasn't some pressure to go
faster or have more nor something and
and if there if that project exists are
they hiring yeah seriously so then you
have all these pressures to do that to
move you forward and and then someone's
gonna you know make it hard for you to
do a bunch of stuff and and most
developers will start to kind of color
outside the lines if it's the if it's
really really hard to do the right thing
unless you have kind of draconian
culture you know really highly regulated
whatever process then most people are
gonna they're gonna err on the side of
of Yolo and and do whatever they can to
get things done
push the
red button so one you mentioned puppet
can you tell us a bit about what that is
oh so puppet is a project that I used to
have I spent all my time on it and it's
a configuration management tool that
allows you to configure servers based on
a policy so you would write these puppet
manifests that describe how a server
should be should be configured and then
that's a that's its own language that
has you know some rich abstractions
around things like users and groups and
files and and all the things that really
is like a system administrator should
concern themselves with and now it's
even more sophisticated and there's
integrations to the networking gear and
and the storage gear and the rest of it
too but that the model is basically that
you have this declarative you know
rule-based policy that specifies how
servers should be configured and then
that allows you to maintain consistency
across relatively large relatively
sophisticated servers and it's a great
tool especially in in a model where
you're all about pinning the states or
the mental model for those that
generation of tools is really about
getting a server into a certain state
and you know really to be quite honest
keeping it there it's it's about pinning
the state and that that's great in a
time when you had maybe not so many
servers and applications were developed
on top of them but you you weren't
really trying to do deployments with the
same basically violent frequency that
you're seeing now with the continuous
delivery models and so when you when you
get to the to the thing where you're
trying to both go faster at a higher
scale then then coordinating those
declarative models across a large
infrastructure it can be done and and
I've done it it just requires filling in
a lot of coordination and orchestration
code so that you can do those
deployments and it's not purpose-built
to do that like claps Andria's is the
solar platform is
like 500 that is the that is sort of the
at scale version of that discipline it's
not a question about scale or not a
scale what Cloud Foundry is doing is
shifting the the primitive from being a
server centric primitive to an
application centric or service centric
primitive so I don't think it's a
question of scale and you know certainly
I know puppet and chef deployments
they're there on the order of you know
hundreds of thousands of servers sure
and they work great at the way you know
the level they're designed but then they
actually integrated you know user
experience to do deployments is very
different than you're gonna get from
something like Heroku oh and and Heroku
use some of these tools as well to build
that but then like what's the user
experience for the actual developer
what's the user experience for the the
operator and what is that experience if
you're not a hundred percent familiar
with all those tools right so it's one
thing if you're an expert on the tool to
make good use of it it's another to kind
of pick it up and use it the first day
was that experience there's a cloud
foundry or Heroku give you a smoother
on-ramp in the end trade-off you know a
bit of flexibility does it trade-off
more power I think I think in many
regards you have more flexibility with
something like puppet but you could
because you can do anything you wanted
right where where what Cloud Foundry has
done is collapse some of those options
into this very opinionated cognitive
twelfth factor model so that you're get
you're able to do the rapid deployment
it's a great user experience for the
developer and it's also a more and more
a great user experience for the operator
but in some ways is less flexible right
so before we get too far ahead what are
we talking about when we say cloud
funder what is that today Cloud Foundry
has it's actually a fascinating story
and there's a bunch of things I
say publicly because I don't too much
but and I I wasn't involved in all this
I was kind of watching from the
sidelines I know a bunch of the
characters but Cloud Foundry started as
a project at VMware and the majority of
the early engineers on Cloud Foundry had
all kind of come from behind the veil at
Google and they were specifically hired
to work on this this deployment fabric
so they'd they'd seen bored they'd
worked on the the Google infrastructure
such they sres and engineers that were
paid you know quite handsomely to come
work on Cloud Foundry inside VMware and
they they worked on the you know the
first versions of what is now Cloud
Foundry but at some point internally
there's you know there's a bunch of
politics and and personalities and so
Cloud Foundry made its way from from
VMware into pivotal and pivotal was spun
off as assets from from VMware and EMC
for live reasons but I think mostly to
kind of free them up to to be a little
bit more focused on the future without
the you know so many connections to the
existing businesses that the EMC and
VMware have and and give us a little
more freedom to really go go hard at
building that future and and now that
that base architecture has been really
adapted and evolved following the and
and everything's been refreshed by
pivotal labs which pivotal has a long
history of doing a ton of application
development particularly for startups
but even now more and more we're doing
work and partnering with enterprise
customers but the early days of Twitter
or Google Luber all these places did
their projects with with pivotal labs
and so now the the project that that we
have Cloud Foundry is it's a hundred
percent pair programming it's pretty
much test-driven development religiously
they they have that you know
strict XP engineering practices that's
this is how payroll does all their work
right now at least on the on the lab
side we have a different a lot of
different pockets of engineers that have
been left to sort of whatever their
their cultural practices were but at
least four pivotal labs there's a
there's a long tradition of really
strict XP practices and that's the Cloud
Foundry team right now I see and so
cloud finally the project is open source
yeah Cloud Foundry is open source so
there's a foundation there's on paper
about a trillion dollars of market cap
supporting the foundation I've always
been a big fan of foundations in general
you know anything about meteor
yeah watch anything but the the way that
the Cloud Foundry foundation got set up
there are some things that were put in
place to I think they watched a lot of
the stuff that happened with some of the
other foundations and some of the other
projects and they and they try to they
try to put in place really strict
stewardship who's they
the the people that were in the position
to create the foundation so James
ladders robbed me that it's a you know
whatever the executive leadership from
pilla and whoever agree to it from
places like IBM and HP and the rest of
it but the emphasis is on is on the
functionality and the stewardship of the
code not necessarily protecting people's
feelings of inclusiveness right so who
administers this foundation is it held
by pivotal no so the there's an
independent nonprofit organization those
created and you know that's really
ramping up and the the people that are
there are it like well I said um I was
previously very skeptical about
foundation it's a it's been a pleasure
to work with chip shoulders and the Sam
Ramsey's and the it's basically a
organization that is following some of
the
and back end from the Linux Foundation
but then it's also independent so Sam
Sam Ramsey who I think he's the perfect
person for this he was he was
instrumental at some of the stuff that
really got Microsoft set on an
open-source path so some of the CodePlex
work and some of the you know early
things where Microsoft started to get a
clear around open source well it was
really foundations that were laid by Sam
Ramji and now I mean you look at what's
going on with Microsoft nor I'm shocked
to see some of the stuff with their open
sourcing right now and and I don't know
you know how much cry you can give Sam
for that but I think you have to get in
at least a little bit of it and watching
him in Cloud Foundry and the vision that
he has for being able to maintain the
the stewardship of the project that also
created collaboration community I'm
really looking forward to how that all
comes together and you know the first
event that the foundation is doing is
actually going to be a week from today
on Monday instead it's the first cloud
foundry summit that's been run by the
foundation and then we're looking
forward to seeing a bunch of that
community share their stories and their
and their successes there they're
literally transforming their industries
adopting this technology cool so this
foundation it's it's a from an
administrative perspective it's a it
seems like that's a win from a user's
perspective the cloud foundry is open
source and now it's being managed by
this foundation which would you describe
it as more of a meritocracy or what is
it I never use that word okay how would
you describe it then what is I don't I
don't use words that were introduced
into the language as the title of a
dystopian novel to describe anything
sensible or good all right so the way
that is couched in language is its
governance by contribution right which
in in most sense whenever someone saying
meritocracy it basically means the
people who are in charge are going to
tell you if they're in charge you never
see someone who's not in charge talking
about the merits of meritocracy and with
that you know governance my contribution
basically means that you know we
we want everyone to write the code and
the more code you write the more code
you know the more say you get by virtue
of the fact that you're that you're
writing the code and you know in some
mental models of what meritocracy might
look like then that could be a very
similar model but it's it's explicit
what it what is meant by merit in that
case instead of just good feelings well
well I think that the problem with
meritocracy in general is that mary is
defined by the people who have merit so
by definition they're they're all Oleg
are keys they just don't want to realize
it I see so this contribution model then
it is welcomed other community
contributions I mean is this now a going
concern you mentioned a trillion dollar
market cap on paper who are some of the
players so so this is one of the things
that you know and this is something
we're trying to fix and that will segue
into it we should talk about lattice to
to kind of end this but the Cloud
Foundry as a as a framework envisioned
inside of someplace like like VMware
having the understanding of what it took
to run Google was was kind of a
all-or-nothing solution right and and
that is a big pill to swallow
if you're a lone developer trying to to
have an experience so out-of-the-box
right now for someone to go as a single
person without pretty deep understanding
of all this stuff and get up to speed on
on bosh and doing the performance and
having Cloud Foundry working in a
production quality set up then that
that's a pretty heavy lift and that's a
pretty big pill to swallow so the the
ecosystem that that was created and also
because of a bunch of other features
that we didn't really talk about they
have to do it so we sort of focus a
little bit on the developer experience
and then sort of did this hand waving
about operating and being able to do
recovery and managing these things of
scale but there's a bunch of other stuff
that's built into Cloud Foundry that is
specifically
to address things like large
organizations and and role based
authentication and access to resources
and the sophisticated role role based
service broker model and those things
make a lot of sense when you have
hundreds or thousands of developers and
you're wanting to manage you know
hundreds of resources and make sure the
right people have the right access they
don't make sense when you're one
developer trying to build your your next
big thing in your dorm room and and so
then there's a there's a little bit of a
you know kind of top-down adoption
problem that you at least you know my
background and the community stuff that
I've been involved with in other open
source projects makes it so that you
just is it's hard to get people excited
about something that's like such a huge
pill to swallow and has a bunch of
features that they don't see the value
of because because they're there one guy
in a dorm room right they can't I wanted
to get it going they couldn't they
couldn't bootstrap so what is the what's
the middle ground there how do you get
those features and and still start in
your in the proverbial dorm room well I
mean the adoption that you're seeing
inside of the enterprise and the people
that need that kind of functionality has
has been you know frankly just exceeds
my expectations but then back to your
point the the features and the
technology that's being built to deliver
this platform has value outside of the
context of that full platform and we
were able to demonstrate that and this
was just this was just announced
recently with with lattice and what
lattices is Cloud Foundry by subtraction
and it is is taking away the the role
based authentication it's taking away
some of the the orgs and the and the
workflows and the and the built acts and
it's just exposing the container
scheduler this routing layer this HTTP
routing layer that is keyed off of
health checks and then some operational
assistance with the log aggregation and
it's also been pared down so that and
and the you know the guarantees that
you're getting out of the box are maybe
not quite so it's not as resilient out
of the box is a wash deployed Cloud
Foundry but you're you're able to get a
set up in minutes on on vagrant or four
minutes on digital ocean or Amazon or
Google there's this guy Matt from Cisco
just did a installation for OpenStack so
you can do it on OpenStack now too
for you cause you don't know protect
that you'd have to have done it yourself
and and so that means they in five to
ten minutes you could get a little last
cluster and start pushing applications
into it and and seeing that resolve and
having that you know whatever the the
endorphins and and the then serotonin or
whatever that you get from from playing
with these kind of toys and now I don't
know you've been even using ladders as
well so what is your impression of that
having seen the evolution and you know
the the stuff that's available in Cloud
Foundry to to lattice me I I'm just I
like the ability to work in terms of
containers so now I have this very
natural way to deploy applications and
move them manage them and so on locally
and I I sort of wonder will that
experience be mirrored now if I wanted
to go you know if I do want to go into
this production system and inside of a
larger enterprise you know back it back
in the cloud fender world is that store
what does that look like what's the next
version of crowdfunder are gonna do to
to offer that same experience so what
lattice represents is isolating the
diego rewrite of the elastic runtime
which has support for docker and making
darker the deployment artifact is that
the only supported one or does it
support others on lattice or lattice or
500 so right now lattice is the only
lasts only deploys docker unless you
really know how to get into the guts of
it and then you can do some stuff and we
we saw this today one of our co-workers
did a because he made last work on
Windows and so he he what he did is he
he used the the windows build packs to
build the the actual droplet container
and then he extracted that and then he
forced it into lattice so there's a
little bit coloring outside the lines
and you kind of had to know how the
internals of some of that stuff works to
pull it off but the fact that he proved
you could do it means that you could
wrap some tooling around that and make
it a little better experience so Cloud
Foundry will not go away from the build
path model but but it will support
docker as a first-class deployment
artifact as well and then there's also
probably going to be rocket support and
potentially the the fact is like these
are really thin wrappers around the
cgroups of namespace stuff and so you
know figuring out how you're gonna get
your metadata for what processors be run
and where you're gonna get your
filesystem
isn't that hard you know there there's
nuance differences between the different
options but then going back to something
I talked about earlier I I think it's
dangerous to go to a full mystery meat
container model if you don't know what
those route file systems are based on
then your your potential exposure is
infinite I mean or as bad as you don't
want and we've had customers that are
requesting that the docker support be be
turned off and and that was you know
it's trivial to you knowing but but it's
also if you think about the you know
going back to the hygiene discussion we
had earlier if you if you have a bunch
of different things that are based on
random route file systems and you don't
know what those are and you don't have a
great inventory of them that you can
algorithm ically go and and and patch
and and manipulate then if you have a
thousand of those in production and you
have a security concern then then what
are you going to do that day where if
you if you got a bill
tract model which guarantees the the
hyejung by providing a single root
filesystem or or you know selected
subset of root file systems and then
curated maybe no I mean I I could build
you a hygienic docker built pipeline and
it would be all docker and you could
have some of these benefits it's just
that that's not the way that a lot of
people are adopting this technology
right now and so they they I mean this
guy exactly what I said earlier like
they're just thinking about day one like
how do I get this as a running process
into this thing but they're not thinking
about all the inevitable inevitable
issues that they're gonna have to
resolve day two and forward so does this
technology represent does this inclusion
represent a sort of a hybrid opportunity
if you need that drop hatch to to escape
into mystery meat land you've got it but
for the for the 80% case prefer the
hygienic sort of build pack sterilized
you know you know what you're gonna get
it we know how to manage it kind of
world and now you can have both of those
run by side side by side so the way I
would probably want to about this if it
was my organization and I'm in charge is
that you want to have the ability for
people to color outside the lines enough
to experiment with new technologies and
take advantage of of the innovation it's
a possible but then I would have a
little more rigor about what I consider
production so then you know that I would
I would be reluctant to put mystery meat
into production but I certainly don't
want to limit my my own use cases in my
own developers when when you're doing
prototypes and spikes on on ideas so
then to me it's about it's about getting
through well you know whatever is the
fastest thing to validate a thing I mean
I guess here's the here's the dirty
little secret of pretty much the whole
software industry is that most of what
people have in production are prototypes
and and I think that with a little bit
more rigor and processed and then you
can actually do some things that make
things you know quote-unquote production
in a way that reduces your ongoing
operating costs so then and
one of the things that people talk about
in the in the DevOps movement and
recognizing operations is a competitive
advantage if you think about what it
takes to run a service if there's any
cost at all to run a service then
there's always some time line where that
cost exceeds every other cost that
detected involve it assuming the service
runs long enough right that's what I
mean on some timeline yeah so if it's
very very expensive to run something
then you exceed that rather quickly and
if it's not expensive then then it might
be you know heat death of the universe
or nearly forever right
so so if you if you can get a huge
impact in your operational efficiency by
following some things even if they might
seem slightly inconvenient on the front
side then the payoff over time is is
considerable so for the 80% case then
for the applications for the things that
people are developing for the 90% case
even that seems to be a very natural way
to go right you want that consistency
and then perhaps you mentioned
prototypes for me this is my personal
like everyone has different
sensibilities like firstly would argue I
think for production I mean I would run
as hygienic as possible in in I would
never want to constrain what someone
could do on their laptop or what someone
could do in the test environment but
then then the question is like where the
extra steps to take whatever they did
and put that into our hygienic process
right and so going through and saying
okay well here's what you did
here's your image here's these artifacts
and then either creating the new build
pack or doing some other thing to get
that ongoing benefit I'll make that
investment and kind of keep that
pristine hygienic production environment
I see okay so for example if you're the
the youth case I sort of was attracted
to was okay I have these ready to use
images of or containers that will get me
you know elasticsearch or something like
that
sure and that becomes a service broker
in the parlance of plat funding that's a
the mechanism that integrates whatever
thing you're trying to run as a service
as a backing service into the framework
that Cloud Foundry can can run it but it
is nice to be able to just stand it up
for prototyping and get it working and
inside of a container that's great
that's great now you have a fruit for
the concept that you could work with
elasticsearch that the service broker
looks and elasticsearch but that is not
the same thing in my opinion as really
operationalizing elasticsearch in such a
way that six months from now when
there's a new security patch for
elasticsearch that you're able to do the
right thing effectively so you're saying
move that to a service broker eventually
or so get it up prototype and then move
it into the framework which in that case
would be a service broker okay
build a proper no it's not about the
service broker it's about the
orchestration of the lifecycle that as a
service itself whether you throw in a
service broker or not is sort of an
independent consideration but it's
really about so you you pulled the
mystery meat elasticsearch now what are
you going to do what do you know what
the kernel I mean the the you know
whatever like the dependencies of all
that were you know when when there's a
new security thing what it was well you
have you have a bunch of these things
that you can kind of pre and this is a
this is the best way I think of it and
this might relate to is people who are
really focus on development is people
get really spun up about things like you
know static typing versus dynamic typing
and like you know why functional
programming is better than
object-oriented programming and vice
versa
and the difference here is is very
similar in that if you if you allow
people to do whatever they want in to
you know whatever package roof all
system then that's kind of like dynamic
typing and it mostly works but there's a
whole bunch of problems that it causes
later and people have written about you
know their their transition from things
like you know the Alex Payne from from
Twitter wrote a big thing about is a
experience transitioning from rulli and
you know Scala and some of these other
typing systems but if you think about
things clearly on the front side which
is where a static typing system forces
you to do then it eliminates a bunch of
other problems that you can have later a
class of errors you wouldn't have
exactly a cat box a class of errors just
go away
like you don't you eliminate that
problem by not having it
Alex pain of course went on to start
Bank simple so if we extrapolate if you
a new remove enough errors you too can
start a bank or something anyway that's
how logic works yeah naturally we've
just looked at lattice any eyes want to
dot there anything any t's went across I
just think I mean lattice is sort of a
nascent experiment to try to get Cloud
Foundry technology out there I think
that the early indication is that it's a
it's a thing that people like I
certainly like playing with it for my
own my own work it gives you a nice
little way to do to do deployments and
really get the power of the scheduling
and the and the routing you know there's
a bunch of other things going on like
this is not a static space and there's
other people working on things are doing
similar things you know I don't know how
much you want to spend talking about the
the rest of it but core LS had a
coalesced fest today and you know the
stuff they're doing with kubernetes and
and some of the other stuff that's going
on in you know both the docker ecosystem
and and rocket and mess house is just an
exciting time to see everyone working on
on solving these problems even though
they're they're all slightly different
but they're all they're all kind of the
same - do you see it as sort of a
validation that we're all at least
trying to solve the same problems that
means we're as an industry we're on in
the same space well the funny thing
there is you know if you think about the
history of cloud foundry and the mess
and kubernetes in some sense it
represents the Diaspora of the of the
Google tooling and mindset
I'll kind of go back to this
google-based lineage interesting
interesting which which is why we have
containers and Linux in the first place
there were similar kernel level
isolation mechanisms in in BSD since
like 2000 and and I think Solaris had
them in 2004 and you get them in the
Linux kernel because because Google put
them there
well you had them in the Linux kernel
before but you weren't in the mainline
kernel so you had to apply patches and
you like you had to recompile through
like there's openvz
and some other stuff that the people
that were doing all the the web hosting
really like containers because you could
put you know thousands of websites on on
a single machine and since most of them
are idle you don't really have too much
problems with contention anyway so that
they really like that technology but it
wasn't it wasn't in the mainline kernel
till Google put it there 2.6 is that
right Colonel Burton that's when you
first get the first name spacing I mean
see group stuff so that is actually a
very old release it's nice to see a lot
of the start of congealing and becoming
you know it's now consumable you know
it's a mass so to speak and we also
didn't talk about you know kernels which
have in my opinion all the advantages of
containers but even more so and those
are it's like if you have if you have
the ability to package your application
in such a way that you don't even need
any of the multi-purpose operating
system features like users or rest of
this you just want a service that does
HTTP and doesn't need to manage a bunch
of this other stuff then I think
unicorns are a great approach and if it
follows the same Marcus containers and
people be really excited about 2021
interesting well something to look
forward to so these are a lot of
different technologies where would you
recommend people learn more about this
stuff if you have a minute to point
people in the right direction well
there's a you know obviously all these
things have open source we didn't really
talk about the impact of open source but
I think for the most part infrastructure
going forward well will be based on open
source to some degree you wouldn't you
wouldn't have cloud computing without
without Linux you would have you know
any of this stuff going on without Linux
oh I I really think that trend will
continue so any of those communities are
interesting I I think that it's it's
worth people's time to learn about
operations and and the DevOps
communities are interesting places to
learn about what it takes to actually
run this stuff at scale what it takes to
run this stuff consistently moving
faster and safer you know more
consistent deployments more rapid
deployments all that stuff's happening
what else is going on oh yeah the osv
and and ultra mirage projects are
interesting if you're into the or you
want to find out more about unicorns
interesting and frankly like I think
that you're gonna see more and more of
this in whatever kind of development
communities you're in anyway so you're
seeing some of this bleed into the
conversations you know this the spring
booth is is doing lots of stuff with
lattice now and that that's Sanji is
probably going to increase not decrease
application development is converging
with sort of operations right and that
well this goes back to the point I was
trying to make little bit earlier is
that at the point where you realize well
you know one of the things people will
often say you're on DevOps and you know
some people give me card for
articulating a lot of this is this idea
of infrastructure is code and that gives
you some insight into how this all works
together but at the point where you're
able to provision virtual machines
configure them with with API so
everything's API driven from the the
provisioning to the configuration to
Alec to monitoring to do any deployment
to grabbing the logs to doing you know
what anything that had had been done by
a person doing a task is replaced by an
API then all that work that was with
system administrators running scripts
starts to look suspiciously like
software development so the the platform
itself is software the infrastructure
itself is software software all the way
down its
all the way down to the software and I
knew and there's I mean this is this is
a Depot Rob hose we don't want to go
down that the the Software Defined
Networking the software-defined storage
this this the abstractions are going to
be available as you know the the stuff
that Amazon release with lambda the the
paradigms for how we're going to think
about applications and data and the rest
of it are are going to evolve quite
rapidly in my opinion over the next over
the next decade it doesn't mean that
that everything will change you know
obviously people slower on mainframes
both the dirt that that front edge of
this will will definitely involve fast
very very cool so if people wanted to
get more of your opinion are you on
Twitter I am on Twitter and that's
probably the easiest way to get my
attention my twitter handle is little
idea all one word all spelled out and
I'm I'm usually
I don't know people think I'm okay
because I mostly just say whatever
amuses me but but I definitely like
talking about your distributed systems
and deployment and we didn't talk too
much about people and process today but
I think that the people are big part of
this and and you don't have software
without without people and recognizing
that knowledge work is not the same
thing as digging ditches as a it's also
a big part of this we're we're running
well over time that is definitely a
perhaps in a topic for another episode I
hope you'll consider joining us again
hopefully we didn't we didn't boy
everyone to death but as you can tell
from my rattling headphones I get a
little excited about some of this yeah I
can see why okay well thank you very
much Andrew Andrew clean-shaven for
joining us today as always dear audience
we want to hear from you there are many
ways you can reach us you can comment on
the show on on there on our website
se - radio net or email us at team at SU
radio dotnet our twitter handle is at SU
radio and of course we're on all the
usual social channels LinkedIn Google+
etc software engineering radio groups as
well as on Facebook anything you want to
leave them with there Andrew
so an amazing time to be working on this
stuff and I'm excited to be part of it
and I hope everyone will I think you can
always learn more so just don't stop
learning don't stop building and you
know thanks for having me thank you for
joining us and goodbye
[Music]
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you